Preliminary Guide to the Beth Joselow literary papers, 1968-2001 MS2242
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Beth Joselow literary papers
1968-2001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Joselow, Beth
MS2242
10 Linear Feet
This collection contains correspondence, drafts, and published poems, plays, and prose written by poet and writer Beth Joselow. The collection dates from 1968-2001. Having settled in Washington in 1970-, Beth was part of the Mass Transit Poets in Washington in the early 1970s. This Dupont Circle poetry group held weekly readings, produced five issues of Mass Transit, a poetry magazine, and led to the establishment of Some Of Us Press, which published chapbooks by Michael Lally, Terence Winch, Tim Dlugos, Lynne Dreyer and others.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Beth Joselow in 2008(Accession 2008.083)
Historical or Biographical Note
Poet and writer Beth Baruch Joselow was born in Washington and raised in Baltimore. The city of Baltimore and the people Beth knew while growing up have heavily influenced her poetry, particularly her early work. She began writing poetry seriously in her 20s. Having settled in Washington in 1970-, Beth was part of the Mass Transit Poets in Washington in the early 1970s. This Dupont Circle poetry group held weekly readings, produced five issues of Mass Transit, a poetry magazine, and led to the establishment of Some Of Us Press, which published chapbooks by Michael Lally, Terence Winch, Tim Dlugos, Lynne Dreyer and others. Beth has published poetry, prose and plays, and her work has appeared in numerous magazines and anthologies. She often has collaborated with artists and musicians, in this country and in Russia. Beth is the author of six books of poetry,: Ice Fishing (1974), Gypsies (1978), The April Wars (1983) Broad Daylight (1989). Excontemporary (,1993), and Begin at Once (2007). Her chapbook,: Self Regard, was published by Chax Press in Tucson, AZ in 2000. She is also the author of Writing Without the Muse, a book of creative writing exercises. Beth has been awarded five grants for creative writing from the DC Commission on the Arts and Humanities. Her book, Life Lessons: 50 Things I Learned from My Divorce was published by Avon Books in 1994. Beth was an associate professor teaching writing and liberal studies at The Corcoran School of Art [from 1987 to 2004]. In addition to her Masters in Creative Writing from Johns Hopkins she also earned a M.S. degree in Clinical Community Counseling. Beth has a psychotherapy practice in Lewes, Delaware.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, drafts of poetry, prose, and plays, fliers, journals, magazines, and two audio cassettes. The collection comprises the literary files of author Beth Joselow and reflects her interactions with many poets in the Washington DC area for more than 30 years. The collection includes correspondence and magazines related to Mass Transit and other works related to the Avant Garde poetry movement in Washington, D.C. including the periodicals Mass Transit, Dog City and Everybody's Ex-Lovers. Many local poets are represented in this collection either their published works or in correspondence and other literary files. These poets include among others Doug Lang, Joan Retallack, P. Inman, Doug Lang, Michael Lally, Tina Darragh, Terence Winch, and Phyllis Rosenzweig. In addition to published journals and magazines that include Beth's work, the collection contains numerous folders of drafts of poems, prose, and plays some of which may never have been published at least not in that form.
The books that arrived with this collection including chapbooks published by SOS books and Some of Us Press have been added to the Special Collections' book collection. These materials are accessible through the book catalog. The Special Collections' book collection does not circulate and may only be used in the Special Collections' reading room.
Purchased from Beth Joselow in 2008, (Accession 2007.083 ).
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Correspondence, Literary files, Drafts, and Periodicals.
Washington (D.C.); Audiocassettes; Experimental poetry -- 20th century.; Plays (document genre); Poets, American; Poetry; Joselow, Beth
- Correspondence, 1968-1996; MS2242 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence between Beth Joselow and other writers, publishers, and granting agencies. The records in this series date from 1968-1996.
  - Celia Bland, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carmen Delzell, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Tim] Dlugos, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stephen Donatelli, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Paul Genega, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Harrison Fisher, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Grants and awards, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lit [literary] Business, 1975-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Loose correspondence, 1968-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Howard Moss (the New Yorker), 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Katie Kramer, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mass Transit and S.O.U.P [Some of Us Press] poets, 1974-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A.L. Nielson, 08/05/1992-09/28/1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Poetry correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Poetry correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proposals and submissions, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Queries, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Liam Rector, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - References, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mary Truitt, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Various writers [1/3], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Various writers [2/3], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Various writers [3/3], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Washington area writers, 1983-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Baron Wormser, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Literary files, 1974-1995; MS2242 Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains the literary files of Beth Joselow. These records date from 1974-1995. These records include grant applications and a listing of places Beth submitted her work. There are also records related to the Dupont Circle poetry group Mass Transit.
  - The April Wars - reviews, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Calendar, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    General note
    [American poets greet the earth an annual calendar, proposal for Archtype Press]
  - Catalogs (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Central Conference of American Rabbis, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - DC Grant Ap [application], 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Grant Aps [applications], 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Grants-in-aid Application, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hopkins, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Index cards records of submissions [1/2], circa 1970 - circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Index cards records of submissions [2/2], circa 1970 - circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Literary life [1/2], 1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Literary life [2/2], 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mass Transit, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ana Mendieta, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Miss Lulu Bett, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - NEA AP [application], 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - NEA AP [application], 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - NEA AP 1988 (a) [application], 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - NEA, 1998-2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Portugal, 1990-1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Publicity, 1984-1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    This file contains reviews, event fliers and profiles. Some of the material is not dated.
  - Record of submissions, 1974-1987 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - SOS Books [Sultan of Swat], 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - [Story Line Press], 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Drafts, 1976-1990; MS2242 Series 3; 3.5 Linear feet
  This series contains drafts of poems, prose, and plays. Unless noted in the folder title the works are authored by Beth Joselow. Some of the works in this series are published or became part of published works. These materials date from 1976-1990.
  - An American Voyage by Joe Ross (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The April Wars, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The April Wars, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The April Wars SOS book [Sultan of Swat] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The April Wars drafts, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Baltimore Story [title Eden], 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining at the Beach a trilogy of one-act plays (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Bargaining at the Beach a trio of one-act plays (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Beth Corning, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bread and Butter a play in two acts, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bread and Butter, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bread and Butter a play in two acts, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bread and Butter a play in two acts, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Broad Daylight, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Body of No Sex (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - To David [Alpher or Alplier] [poems] (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Dormer Windows poems (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Drafts, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Drafts of poems (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Drafts, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Drafts of old poems (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Ducks a play in one act (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Ducks (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Eden, Susie Harvey 9/23/1990 and Hattie Powell interview 9/23/1990, 09/23/1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    This folder has a draft of the story and tape cassettes recording the interviews
  - Envy and the Violin by Richard Zenith (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ethan (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Excontemporary (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Fill These Shoes (Box 7, Folder 8)
    from the folder "A production of Corning Dancers & Company, conceived and choreographed by Beth Corning, written by Beth Joselow, directed by Kay Cummings.
  - House Ideas (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Hurry Up Please a play in one act, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Hurry Up Please (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Ice fishing (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - I'll see you in the funny papers, a draft (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Increase Long" simultaneously with "fine", 11/20/1987 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    This document is a hand-out that was used in a reading with Joan Retallack
  - Intros, crit and reviews by BJ [Beth Joselow], 1981-1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - John Cage conversations with Joan Retallack (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Note: the full text appears in Aerial #6
  - Lattice, 01/31/1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    hand-out for reading with Michael Anderson
  - Log [job in/job out poems], 11/21/1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - M.S. [poems etc.] (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - New Voices a showcase of one act plays, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Suzanne by Beth Joselow; Bruises by Jude Adler; Change at Jamaica by Ronni Brenner.
  - Non-fiction mss Eden (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Old Mss rough drafts (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - On the Boards poems, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Pass (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Eventually published as a chapbook.
  - poems, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - poems (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - poems, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - poems (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - poems (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - poems (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - poems and correspondence, 1980-1998 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - poems drafts (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - poems: loose drafts [1/3] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - poems: loose drafts [2/3] (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - poems: loose drafts [3/3] (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - poems: newly finished copies to send out (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - poems old (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Poetry MS 1997 self-regard (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Poetry submissions (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Primary writing #2 3 novels by Doug Lang (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Rattlebone by Maxine Clair [galley proofs] (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Scape poems by Paul Genega, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Story (ies) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - III Survivors [poems] (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Suzanne a play in one act (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Weather Gallery by Liam Rector (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Periodicals, 1973-2001; MS2242 Series 4; 4.5 Linear feet
  This series contains literary journals, newsletters, and magazines. Most of these are poetry publications and in many of them Beth Joselow's work is included. All donated periodicals have been retained in the collection regardless if Beth's work appeared because these materials share with a researcher the works that Beth feels are important to keep as an historical record.
  - Abacus, 1986-1992 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    There are 3 issues in this folder.
  - Aerial #3, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Aerial #4, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Aerial #5, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Aerial 6/7, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - The American Poetry Review, 07/1981-08/1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Anomoly issue no. 1, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Anomoly issue no. 2, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - The Bellingham Review Vol. 5 no. 1, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Big Allis no. 3, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Big Allis no. 4, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Big Allis no. 7, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Big Ideal 3, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Bird A Fly-By-Night Journal of D.C. Poets, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Bingo Chow, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    The folder has two issues.
  - The Blackbird Circle no. 5, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Bogg no. 62, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Discovering Motherhood, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - District Lines the Magazine for Young Writers issue #1, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Dog City, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Dog City no. 2, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Everybody's Ex-lover [EEL], 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    The folder has three issues. Nos. 1,3 and possbily 2.
  - Epoch, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Exquisite Corpse, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    This folder has six issues.
  - Exquisite Corpse, 1987-1993 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    This folder has ten issues.
  - Exposures issue 1, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Exposures issue 2, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Frank an international journal of contemporary writing and art no. 6/7, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Goethe's Notes no. 1, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - the G.W. Review Vol. 2 no. 1 - Vol. 3 no. 1, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    The folder has five issues.
  - the G.W. Review Vol. 6 no. 1 - Vol. 6 no. 2, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - GW Washington Studies no. 11, 06/1984 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Title "Evidence of Community: writing from the Jenny McKean Moore Workshops at George Washington University
  - Hanging loose no. 27, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Hanging loose no. 28, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Hanging loose no. 42, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Hoo-Doo no. 4 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Hot Bird MFG Vol. 1 no. 11, 02/1991 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - How(ever) Vol. 6 no. 4, 01/1992 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - The National Jewish Monthly, 01/1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Kalliope a journal of women's art Vol. 9 no. 3, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Kalliope a journal of women's art Vol. 12 no. 3, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - The Lamp in the Spine no. 6, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - The Little Magazine Vol. 9 no. 2, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Loose Art no. 1 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - The Love Project anabasis no. 2, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - lower limit speech a newsletter in poetics #1-13 [no #12] (Box 14, Folder 13)
    The folder has twelve issues.
  - The Manhattan Review Vol. 5 no. 1, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Mass Transit a magazine of DC poets no. 1 - no. 5, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - membrane 2, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Mirage The Women's Issue #3, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Mississippi Review no. 30, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - New. no. 24, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - The New Yorker, 03/13/1978 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - New Boston Review Vol. 4 no. 1 - Vol. 5 no. 5/6, 1978-1980 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    The folder has four issues.
  - Open 24 Hours #12, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Painted Bride Quarterly no. 36, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Phoebe the george mason review, 1974-1980 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Pivot no. 34, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Plum no. 1, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - The Poetry Project #132,133, 138, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    The folder has three issues.
  - Potomac Vol. 10 no. 1, Vol. 11 no. 1, Vol. 11 no. 2, 1968-1969 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Primary Writing #3, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - The Reaper, 1982-1987 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Rhino Vol. 4 no. 2, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Roof IX, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - The Salmon Nos. 16,17,20, 1986-1989 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Salt Lick Vol. 4 nos. 1,2, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Shiny the magazine of the future nos. 5 and 7/8, 1990-1992 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - So to Speak a feminist journal of language and art, 1998-1999 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - So to Speak a feminist journal of language and art, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Sun & Moon a journal of literature and arts no. 6/7, 1978-1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Sun & Moon a journal of literature and arts no. 9/10, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Sun & Moon a journal of literature and arts no. 11, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Texture, 1991-1995 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    The folder has issues 1-6
  - They, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    The folder has two issues
  - Three Mile Harbor, 1989-1991 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    The folder has three issues. Winter 1989-90, Spring 1990, and Vol. 2 no. 1
  - Three Mile Harbor, 1992-1994 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    The folder has three issues. Vol. 3 no. 1, Vol. 3 no. 2, and Vol. 4 no. 1
  - Toad Hiway nos. 3 and 4, 06/1990-1991 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Upper Limit Music supplements #1 - #4 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Verse Vol. 7 no. 1, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Washington Review Vol. 8 no. 2, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Washington Review Vol. 9 no. 2, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Washington Review Vol. 10 no. 2, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Washington Review Vol. 11 no. 5 and Vol. 12 no. 2, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Washington Review Vol. 14 no. 2 and Vol. 14 no. 3, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Washington Review Vol. 14 no. 4 and Vol. 15 no. 5, 1988-1990 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Washington Review Vol. 16 no. 3 and Vol. 16 no. 4, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    The folder has two issues. The folder includes a special issue devoted to the Mass Transit poets.
  - Washington Review Vol. 16 no. 5 and Vol. 16 no. 6, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Washington Review Vol. 17 no. 5 and Vol. 18 no. 4, 1991-1993 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Washington Review Vol. 19 no. 1 and Vol. 19 no. 6, 1993-1994 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Washington Review Vol. 20 no. 6 and Vol. 21 no. 1, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Washington Review Vol. 21 no. 2 and Vol. 21 no. 3, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Washington Review Vol. 22 no. 3 and Vol. 22 no. 4, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Washington Review Vol. 22 no. 5 and Vol. 22 no. 6, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Washington Review Vol. 23 no. 1 and Vol. 23 no. 2, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Washington Review Vol. 26 no. 4 and Vol. 28 no. 3, 2000-2001 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Water Pik (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Welcom Home, 11/1987-01/1989 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    The folder has four issues: Vol. 4, no. 11, Vol. 5 no. 2, Vol. 5 no. 10, Vol. 6 no. 1
  - Window issue 1, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Wormhole issue 1 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Yes Vol. 5 no. 1, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - 6ix, 1992-1995 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    The folder has five issues. Vol. 2 no. 1, Vol. 2 no. 2, Vol. 3 no. 1, Vol. 3 no. 2, Vol. 4 no. 1